Hi again. In this video,
we're going to learn
about a common strategy
used to resolve
problems in a project.
On top of several other tasks,
it's a project manager's
responsibility
to resolve problems
and remove constraints that are
a detriment to the
project's success.
One way to do this
is to escalate.
Escalation is the process
of enlisting the help of
higher-level project
leadership or
management to remove an obstacle,
clarify or reinforce priorities,
and validate next steps.
Escalation may seem to have
a negative connotation,
but that's not the case
in project management.
In project management,
escalation should be encouraged,
used often, and even celebrated.
Escalations are healthy
and act as a checks and
balances tool to make
sure appropriate
action is being taken.
They can result in speedy
decision-making, and generally,
the quicker a
problem is resolved,
the better off a project will be.
Instead of going back and forth
between two team members
who can't agree,
an objective third
party might help make
the call and reduce
frustrations within the team.
Finally, escalations
encourage participation.
Encouraging others to
participate in solving or owning
problems can promote trust and
shared responsibility
among teammates,
which are signs of a
healthy, functional team.
Before starting work on a
project, the project manager,
the team, and the
project sponsor should
establish escalation
standards and practices.
This means they'll specify
who the issues will be raised to,
how issues are raised,
and the forum for discussion.
A little upfront work
will help escalations run
smoothly when and
if they're needed.
So you know what an
escalation is and when to
set the framework for
managing escalations,
but how do you know
when to escalate?
A project manager should
escalate an issue at
the first sign of critical
problems in the project.
Critical problems are
issues that may cause
a delay to a major
project milestone,
issues that cause
budget overruns,
issues that can result in
the loss of a customer,
and issues that push back
the estimated project
completion date.
Basically, anything that will
affect your triple constraint,
time, budget, and scope
is something that
should be escalated.
Escalation is great for
preventing two common
issues within a project:
trench wars and bad compromises.
Trench wars occur when
two peers or groups can't
seem to come to an agreement, and
neither party is
willing to give in.
This leads to a standstill
of the project and will
likely delay certain aspects
of the project's progress.
Typically, we think
of compromises
as a positive way
to resolve issues,
but there is such a thing
as a bad compromise.
A bad compromise occurs when
two parties settle on
a so-called solution,
but the end product
still suffers.
When it comes to compromising
on important project goals,
it's not productive
for either party to
settle simply because
it's a means to an end.
Yes, compromise
while also keeping
the larger project goals in mind
and working towards
those together.
You may have to help
your team or stakeholders
make hard choices
for the greater good.
So now we've defined escalation,
how to use the triple
constraints model when
communicating to stakeholders
and negotiating changes,
and we learned about trench
wars and bad compromises,
which are two common
issues on a project.
In the next video,
we'll explain some
more techniques
for communicating with your team,
including timeouts
and retrospectives.
I'll meet you there.